And off, we are effectively a דף daf. *daf* ahead, so we'll
work with that. It's coming up to פסח *Pesach*, I'm sure that
we'll be glad for that when that comes around. So today's דף
daf, *daf* is ס"ט *samekh tes*, 69. We picked up towards the
bottom of ס"ח עמוד ב' bet. *samekh ches amud bais*, and we
are right before the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, five lines into the wide
lines, four lines. ולא בביברין של חיה ושל עוף ושל דגים *v'lo
bivrin shel chaya v'shel of v'shel dagim*. So this is a ברייתא
*braisa* that says when somebody buys a town, he does not buy
the enclosures that have these wild animals and birds and fish. רמינהו
*rami neihu*, and I'll ask you on this: היו לו בנות *hayu
lo banos*, if the town had sister... daughters' towns, like suburbs, outlying
towns, they don't go with it. היו לו חלק אחד בים וחלק
אחד ביבשה *hayu lo chelek echad bayam v'chelek echad bayabasha*, now let's
say the town actually was part on land and part on an
island, like it extended over, there was a body of water that
sort of separated half of the town from the other half, or
בביברין של חיה ושל עוף ושל דגים *bivrin shel chaya v'shel of
v'shel dagim*, or it had enclosures of wild animals, like or like
a nature preserve, הרי אלו נמכרים עמה *harei elu nimkarim imah*, they
are sold with it. So here we have a contradiction about this
issue about these enclosures. Are they really nature preserves? I don't know
what they are. Okay. לא קשיא *lo kashya*, it's not difficult.
But the point is it's not just like a cage of animals,
it's some plot of land. We're dealing with what was the land
that was sold with it. לא קשיא הא דנגיח כאיעי לגב והא
דנגיח כאיעי לבר *lo kashya ha d'nagich ka'ihei lgav v'ha d'nagich ka'ihei
lvar*. I don't even know, can't exactly translate each word there, but
the basic point is, was the, is the opening of these enclosures
towards the town, or is the opening of it outside of the
town? If the opening is towards the town, then they are seen
as an extension of the town. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
והא קתני ולא חורשין המוקצין לה *veha katani v'lo horeshin hamuktzin lah*,
but you also don't sell the forests that are designated for the
town, and that would seem to be what's the difference between that
and the enclosures? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that are open
into the town. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אימא המוקצין הימנה
*emah hamuktzin mimena*. No, no, no, you have to slightly, little edit.
It's not the forests that are designated for the town, it's the
forests that are separated from the town. That's not sold, but the
forests that are designated are sold. So even though the simple sense
of the ברייתא *braisa* says you don't sell the forest, you don't
sell these enclosures of these animals, these you know, nature preserves of
these animals, according, in order so that it shouldn't contradict this other
ברייתא *braisa*, we basically have it say that you do sell it
with it. All right, that's the end of the discussion of selling
the town. המוכר את השדה *hamocher es hasadeh*, interesting, you know, the
order that it went with. Like, first it sort of did like
residential, right? It did house, courtyard, town, right? And even though town
seems like such larger proportion, and now it's doing like, you know,
commercial or agricultural. And now we're dealing with selling a field. So
you sell your field.
מכר את האבנים שהן לצורכה *machas shel avanim shehein
ltzorkah*,
you sell the stones that are necessary for the field, and there's
an interesting difference with this משנה Mishnah *mishnah* that the רשב"ם Rashbam
*Rashbam* tries to exactly figure out like how does it fit the
principles. But you might remember before from things like the bathhouse and
those things, that even like the equipment that is a necessary part
of it, if it's not nailed down, it's not sold with it.
And here some of the, I don't know if you call it
equipment, sometimes it's equipment, sometimes it's just physical objects, but even though
they are not מחובר *mechubar*, they are sold with it if they
are a necessary part of the functions of the field. All right,
so that's a difference between the field and the other things. The
רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* tries to figure out like maybe these are more
necessary, maybe you don't remove these as much as you would remove
the other things. But it is true in this משנה mishnah. *mishnah*
they don't need to be nailed down. המוכר את השדה מכר את
האבנים *hamocher es hasadeh machas shel avanim*, you sell the stones שהן
לצורכה *shehein ltzorkah* that are needed for it. We'll see in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* what type of stones are needed for what you
do in the field. ואת הקנים שבכרם שהן לצורכו l'tzorko *ve'es hakanim
shebakarem shehein ltzorko*, and the sticks that are in the vineyard, the
type of the trellises שהן לצורכו *shehein ltzorko* that are needed for
the vineyard. ואת התבואה שהיא מחוברת לקרקע *v'es hatzvuah shehi mechuberes l'karka*,
the grain that's still connected to the ground. That should be pretty
obvious. You're selling a field of grain, it goes with the grain.
ואת חיצת הקנים שהיא פחותה מבית רובע *v'es chitzas hakanim shehi p'chusa
mibeis rova*, and like a, a section of growing reeds that is
less than a בית רובע bes rova, *beis rova*, a certain type
of a size. So that's considered just like obviously just like a
patch within the field, it's not its own entity. ואת השומירה שאינה
עשויה בטיט she'eina asuya betit. *v'es hashomira
she'eina asuya b'tit*, and a guard's hut that is not plastered over.
Now actually there is, there is two גרסאות *geirsos* of this משנה
Mishnah *mishnah*. This is going to be, the contrast is obviously going
to be that if it is plastered or tarred over, it's not
sold with it. So the logic of that is because then it's
like its own independent structure and then it's like not sold automatically
with the field. Some have the reverse גרסא girsa *geirsa*, that if
it is tarred over, it's more like a piece of the ground
and therefore it's sold with the ground, and if it's not tarred
over, it's more like a separate entity and you know. and more
like a movable and then it's not sold. Anyway, it's surprising! If
you sold a house, you'd even sell the well in a house.
I understand. Field, that's what I was saying before, that I didn't
use the well example, but I used the מטלטלין metaltelin example. You
do wind up selling more things here as part of the field.
I understand. It's not exactly clear why, is it the same rule
and it's just that like, that's what the רשב"ם Rashbam tries to
say: same rule but these are more fixed in these locations whereas
opposed to the other things they move more. You're right, the well
doesn't move more. Or maybe it's just two different rules in place.
שמירה? shmira? A שומרה shomera could be like the סוכה sukkah of
the garden. Yeah, that's exactly what it is, כסוכה בכרם. kesukkah bekarem.
Right. So it depends how you consider it. Exactly. The question of
the גירסאות girsot is, is it more part of the field if
it's tarred over and permanent or is it more part of the
field if it's not tarred over? More of sort of like an
add-on to the field as opposed to its own thing. Okay. ואת
החרוב שאינו מורכב, v'et hacharuv she'eino murkav,
a carob tree that has not been grafted onto. Apparently, when the
carob tree was young, you would not yet graft onto it and
then it would be considered like less significant in its own right.
So if it's a young carob tree. ואת פסולת השקמה, v'et pasulat
hashikmah, and that's a phrase also for a young sycamore tree. So
these things, when they would become older and start to have getting
cut their branches and grafted onto and so on, they would actually
not just be seen as a tree growing in the field, they'd
be like so big and significant they'd be seen as their own
entity. So therefore, but when they're still young, they're part of the
field. Okay. But if the field was sycamores, that's a whole thing.
Yeah, I assume that that would be a different story, obviously. אבל
לא מכר לו את האבנים שאינם לצרכה, aval lo machar lo et
ha'avanim she'einam l'tzarkah, now the next part of the משנה Mishnah is
almost just the, you could write the next part of the משנה
Mishnah yourself. אבל לא מכר לו את האבנים שאינם לצרכה, aval lo
machar lo et ha'avanim she'einam l'tzarkah, you don't sell the stones that
are not necessary, ולא את הקנים שבכרם שאינם לצרכה, v'lo et hakanim
shebakarem she'einam l'tzarkah, not the wood, the sticks in the vineyard that
are not needed for it, ולא את התבואה שהיא תלושה מן הקרקע,
v'lo et hatvuah shehi tlushah min hakarka, and not the grain that's
already been cut down. בזמן שאמר לו היא וכל מה שבתוכה, bizman
she'amar lo hee v'chol mah shebetochah, however, if you said it and
all of its contents, הרי כולם מכורים, harei kulam mehurim, behold they
are all sold. But notice, the previous list ended early. It stopped
sort of there with the cut down wheat. So בין כך ובין
כך, bein kach uvein kach, even if you say all of its
contents, לא מכר לו את חיצת הקנים שהיא בבית רובע, lo machar
lo et hitzat hakanim shehi b'veit rova, you don't sell a big
section of these growing reeds, ולא את השומרה שהיא עשויה בטיט, v'lo
et hashumra shehi asuyah b'tit, and not the guard hut that is
plastered over, tarred over, ולא את החרוב המורכב ולא את סדן השקמה,
v'lo et hacharuv hamurkav v'lo et sadan hashikmah, and not the
grafted carob and not the older sycamore, the larger sycamore. Now why
are these different? So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam conceptualizes it, he
says, is all these last things are not in the field. They
are actually pieces of ground themselves. They are actually קרקע karka themselves.
Right? Look at that list. A patch of growing reeds,
a hut, anyway, it's attached to the ground. A hut maybe doesn't
fit exactly. Okay. The carob tree and the sycamore tree. So the
רשב"ם Rashbam says, here's the example the רשב"ם Rashbam gives. רשב"ם Rashbam
says, let's say I had three plots of land, A, B, and
C, and I said Michael, I am selling you A and C
and everything that's in it. Do you think you would get B?
No. Okay. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, so B is between it?
Right, but I said everything that's in it. So the רשב"ם Rashbam
says, so if I've got this one big plot of land here
and I have a section that has its own identity, here's a
patch of growing reeds or here's a place where I've got this
big sycamore that people see as separate from the field and I
sell you, I'm selling you the whole field and everything in it,
this isn't in the field, this is its own independent field that's
situated sort of in the middle, but it's not in your field,
it's a separate field. Even if it's a tree? That's what he
says. I don't know the way people, if you, I mean, I
don't know, have you ever seen some of those trees that are
like? Those are huge. Right, ten feet across, a hundred feet high.
So he says you don't look at that as a tree in
a field, that's its own thing. That's what he says. They look
at it as a
field. It can't go anywhere. I'm just telling you what the רשב"ם
Rashbam, says. Actually, trees get huge if there's a forest, they don't
have as much room. Ah, right. All right, we're moving on. That's
the way he explains it. Yes. What's a grafted carob?
That means that you cut a branch from that tree and you
graft a branch from another tree onto it. And therefore it's able
to, I don't like. It could be from a different species? It
could be from a different species, yeah. And then it would be
then it would be invalid to eat? No. The problem about כלאים
kilayim is not necessarily like, the laws of כלאים kilayim don't necessarily
prohibit a special, like they particularly between like grain and grape or
between different types of seeds.
It's
not right. It's not necessarily
כלאים. kilayim. They would be the same species? For instance like you
have an old carob and a young
carob and you've grafted a new carob branch which produces better fruit
than the old. Right, okay. So it
has nothing to do with כלאים. kilayim. Got it. Just to understand
what's being consistent with the other משנה. Mishnah We said כל תשמישיה
kol tashmisheiha or something like that. Not necessarily because this is not
a תשמיש tashmish of the field. Okay, מה אבנים שהן לצרכה, mai
avanim shehen litzarchah,
so what are stones that are used in the field? What, the
hut? What do you think? Hut? Hut might be different. Hut you're
right could probably be different. Hut is the one thing of that
list that really doesn't fit. Okay, מה אבנים שהן לצרכה, mai avanim
shehen litzarchah, what are stones that are needed for the field? הכא
תרגימו אבני דאכפא, hacha targimu avnei de'achfa,
weight stones. Basically what the רשב"ם Rashbam would say is you have
all this wheat. You have like anybody ever rake leaves in their
yard? What do you do so that the wind doesn't blow away
the leaves, right? So you gather up all your wheat, you've even
bundled it up, but you don't want it rolling around or whatever,
you put these weight stones down to keep it in place. עולא
אמר אבנים הסדורות לגדר. Ulla amar avanim hasdurot legader. So you basically
have like piled up stones, even arranged stones, and you're going to
build them into a wall around the yard, but you haven't gotten
to it yet. So that's interesting. It's not actually usable yet; it's
like the materials of something that clearly is going to... but from
the way it's placed, it's clear it's like one step away from
being built into a wall. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says
ותני רבי חייא אבנים צבורות לגדר. vetani Rabbi Chiyya avanim tzevurot legader.
So that's not that they have to be סדורות. sdurot. סדורות sdurot
is like nice rows,
whatever. צבורות tzevurot is just like it's in a big pile. It's
just one big mound. It's not like nice rows, okay? And that's
one stage removed from being ready to be built.
תני סדורות. tani sdurot. All right, switch the גרסה girsa so that
it right, have it say what we said, have it say that
they're
nicely laid down. Now, הכא תרגימו, hacha targimu, now we're going to
go back to our original two versions. הכא תרגימו אבני דאכפא, hacha
targimu avnei de'achfa, here in בבל Bavel we explained it as these
weight stones. So now we're going to look at how would this
play out for a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the
רבנן. Rabbanan. Now, we have not seen רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the רבנן, Rabbanan, although we should have seen it because it sort
of should logically run through our entire פרק perek where רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says that when you sell a vineyard, he says the
רבנן Rabbanan give a list of the things that you sell with
a vineyard, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, המוכר את הכרם
מוכר כל תשמישיה הכרם. hamocher et hakarem mocher kol tashmisheiha hakarem. You
sell all the things that are used. So exactly what is the
law, but clearly רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has a slightly bigger definition
of the things that go with something, even things that are not
so tightly connected, even things that are a little more distant from
how closely connected they are to the space, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says those are sold as well. So now we're going to try
to figure out how that would play out in our case. All
right? So the גמרא Gemara says like this: לרבי מאיר דמתקנן אף
על גב דלא מחתן. leRabbi Meir demitaknan af al gav dela machtan.
According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, once the stones were designated to
be used for the field, you
gather some stones that we need for weight stones and you gather
them up, then they would be sold with the field even if
they had not yet been placed, even if they had not yet
begun to be used ever.
לרבנן, leRabbanan, the Rabbis, who have a narrower definition of what's sold,
דמחתן demachtan only after they have once been used. Just designating them
is not enough. ולעולא דאמר אבנים הסדורות לגדר, uleUlla de'amar avanim hasdurot
legader, according to עולא Ulla that says that it's stones that have
been lined up and ready to be built into a wall, how
would the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir רבנן Rabbanan debate play out for
him? So לרבי מאיר דמתקנן אף על גב דלא סדרן. leRabbi Meir
demitaknan af al gav dela sidran. So according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, it would not be what עולא Ulla said. According to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you would not have to
lay them all out in layers. As long as you gathered some
stones and designated them for the wall, that would be enough.
לרבנן דסדרן, leRabbanan desidran, but according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, it's what
we said, only if you actually laid them out in layers. Okay.
והקנים שבכרם שהן לצרכו, ve'hakanim shebakarem shehen litzarcho, the sticks in the
vineyard that are necessary for it. קני מאי עבידתייהו? kanei mai avidtaihu?
What are you using the sticks for? אמר דבי רבי ינאי קנים
המחולקים
שמעמידים תחת הגפנים. amar devei Rabbi Yannai kanim hamichulakim shema'amidim tachat hagefanim.
The sticks that are sort of divided, you
might also say it's like maybe in a crosshatch type of a
way,
which you put under the vines, which help the vines grow, basically
like trellises. All right? If you take a look at the רשב"ם,
Rashbam the second wide line, he says דקורין להם פשיי"לס. dekorein lahem
fassiels. So I don't know if that Greek French word means anything,
but it sounded a little, the end of it sounded a little
like
trellis. All right. So תוספות Tosafot says the
words מחולקים, michulakim, תוספות Tosafot says it does not mean that you
split the sticks or you cross the sticks, but he says it
means you peeled the sticks so that they don't rot. That's the
way תוספות Tosafot reads the word מחולקים. michulakim. Okay. לרבי מאיר, leRabbi
Meir,
now once again how does this play out between רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and the רבנן? Rabbanan? לרבי מאיר דמשפיין אף על גב דלא
מוקמן. leRabbi Meir demishpayan af al gav dela mokman. According to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
once you have sort of... like
smooth them out, right, sanded them or whatever, even though you have
not yet put them in the ground and erected it, לרבנן הוא
דמוקמן, l'Rabbanan hu d'mokman, only once you've erected it. Okay, ואת התבואה
המחוברת לקרקע, v'es hatvuah hamichuberes l'karka, the grain growing from the ground,
אף על גב דמטא למחצד, af al gav d'matai l'nechtzad, even though
the time has come for it to be cut, maybe you think
כל העומד לקצור כקצור דמי kola omed liktzor k'katzur dami and it
wouldn't be sold? No, as long as it's still physically attached, it's
sold with it. Okay, that's an interesting question, so you have to
is when will that's also a רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir position, so
but either we're not going according to that position or it's different
by מקח וממכר. mekach u'memkar. But that's not our סוגיא sugya right
now. Might be.
וחזיזת הקנים שפחותה מבית רובע, v'chizis hakanim shepichusa mibes rova, and a
section of growing reeds that is smaller than this
בית רובע, this whatever, this certain size. אף על גב דאלים. af
al gav d'alimi. So the point is here we go by this
app by this formal definition of the size, even if those reeds
are very thick and it's like a very you can get a
lot of reeds out of that place, if it's smaller than that
size, it's not sold with it. והשומירה שאינה עשויה בטיט, v'hashomira she'eina
asuya betit, and the hut that is not plastered over, made more
permanent, אף על גב דלא קביעה בארעא, af al gav d'lo kvia
b'ara, and even though it is not even like it's more like
a movable, it's not even really it could actually be moved from
place to place. No, these are things that are,
שאינה עשויה בטיט.
Yeah, you're right. Maybe that would be these are things now that
are not sold. So maybe the חידוש chiddush is that you might
think that it's so trivial, these are things that are sold? No,
we move to the things that are not. Wait, no, did we?
No, these are still the things that are. Yeah, you're right. Thank
you. Confusing me there. Okay, we are still within the things that
are sold, right. Okay, yes, these are still the things that are
sold. Okay, so if it's not plastered over,
I know, it depends which גרסא girsa you have. If you have
the גרסא girsa that the less permanent it is, the more it's
seen as just an add-on to the field, that's our version. So
it's not plastered and even if it's movable, and the more movable
something is, the more it's מטלטלין and the more it doesn't go
with the field, this does go with the field. Right, but if
your גרסא girsa, is the opposite, you'd have to have the opposite
גרסא, girsa, right? It's just a pile of wood lying in the
field if it's not plastered over. Aha, the שקא shaka or the
מה ששקא ma sheshaka structure. Okay,
so it's just like a big pile of wood or something. I
right, like if it's funny, it's somehow because it's more trivial it's
more just okay, it's like just an appendage of the field. But
this is interesting because you didn't say כל מה שבתוכה, kol ma
shebisochah, you just said the field. וחרוב אינו מורכב ובתולת השקמה, v'charuv
eino murkav u'besulas hashikma,
so these young carob and sycamore trees, אף על גב דאלים, af
al gav d'alimi, even if they're very thick, if they're still young
and young meaning that they have yet to be grafted onto, yet
to be cut, the branches cut, then they're seen as part of
the field.
That's what you did sell. אבל לא מחצלת אבנים שאינן לצורכה, aval
lo matzes avanim she'einan l'tzorkah, things that are not necessary. So we're
just going to be a very easy דף. לרבי מאיר דלא מתקנן,
l'Rebbi Meir d'lo mesaknan, so it's one stage earlier than what we
had said before. So for רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir when it was
enough to make them part of the field when you designate them,
here we would be talking about stones that have yet to be
designated. לרבנן, l'Rabbanan, the Rabbis who said that in order to make
them part of the field you have to actually have used them
once and placed them once, דלא מחתן, d'lo machsan, we'll be talking
about stones that were designated but not yet placed. And but so
since it's one stage prior, it's not sold with it. ולאולא דאמר
אבנים הסדורות לגדר, u'l'Ulla d'amar avanim hasiduros legader,
according to Ulla that said we're talking about stones that have been
laid for a building a wall, ולרבי מאיר דלא מתקנן, u'l'Rebbi Meir
d'lo mesaknan, so again, one stage earlier. For רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir,
it's before they were designated. Designating would have been enough. ולרבנן דלא
סידרן, u'l'Rabbanan d'lo sidran, and according to the רבנן Rabbanan is where
it would have been that you did designate them, but unless you've
actually laid them out, it's not yet considered to be connected to
the field. Let's just read a little more. They want to get
through this. It's very just
easy, whatever. ולא קנים שבכרם שאינן לצורכו, v'lo kanim shebakerem she'einan l'tzorko,
not the sticks in the vineyard that are not necessary, are not
like the trellises. So the גמרא Gemara. is actually going to say
rather than we're talking about something of a different function, right, because
the משנה Mishnah you would have thought, the difference between לצורכו and
שאינן לצורכו, she'einan l'tzorko, etc., would not have been talking about the
same thing but earlier in the process. Your simple reader of the
משנה would have been we'd be talking about something that has a
different type of a function. But the גמרא Gemara. is sort of
simplifying it and saying rather than talking about different types of stones,
different types of sticks, we're just talking about the fact that they're
not as yet connected because they haven't been designated or used as
much. So the same way it did that with the stones, it
does it with the sticks. ולא קנים שבכרם שאינן לצורכו, v'lo kanim
shebakerem she'einan l'tzorko, לרבי מאיר דלא משפיין, l'Rebbi Meir d'lo mashpuyan, so
רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, it would be the sticks that they have
not yet been like sanded and like smoothed out because for him
that would be enough. ולרבנן דלא מוקמן, u'l'Rabbanan d'lo mokman, and the
רבנן, Rabbanan, even if the trellis has been made, if it has
yet to be sort of erected into the ground, it's not yet
considered connected. So again, the משנה sounds like we're talking about different
types of stones or different types of sticks. The גמרא Gemara. says
no, we're just talking at an earlier stage. Wait, so if they
are according to the רבנן Rabbanan
if they were
מוקמן, mokman, yeah,
then. You do verbal
תיקון *tikun*. That's sort of what Michael is asking.
That's what the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* is saying. The רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
says where's the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*? He says כיון דמתקנות ומזומנות לצרכה
אמרין *Keivan demetukanot umezumanot letzorcha omrin*. מזומנות *Mezumanot*, that you've
done
something to it? Maybe it's not totally verbal, like maybe you actually
picked them up and placed them somewhere, but it doesn't seem like
you physically changed it.
I'm not so sure that you changed it anyway. It seems to
me the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s classic distinction it always deals with is like הזמנה
מילתא היא *hazmana milsa hi*, הזמנה לאו מילתא היא *hazmana lav milsa
hi*. Is designating enough or do you actually have to begin to
use it? But maybe you're right, maybe it's a little bit more
than verbal, but I'm not sure you actually changed physically the object.
Could have been just you picked it up and put it aside
for that purpose. Yes? Maybe I'm reading in the wrong place, but
it says ואף על פי שרומחתן שאינן מונחות לתוך הבסיס אלא חוץ
לבסיס *v'af al pi sheromachtan sheinan munachot l'toch habasis ela hutz labasis*.
רומחתן *Romachtan*. שאינן מונחות *Sheinan munachot*. Right, so they're not... it's not
just a verbal thing. Right, that's what I said. It could be
that you picked them up and moved them somewhere to be used
for that purpose, but I don't know if it means that you
actually did something physical to change them.
I know תיקון *tikun* usually means you did actually something to make
them prepared them, you physically changed something about it. I don't know
exactly what the מתקנן *metaknan* stage is. Alright. ולא את התבואה הצבוטה
מן הקרקע *V'lo et hatevua hatzvuta min hakarka*, not the grain once
it's been harvested, ואחר דצריכא לארעא *v'achar detzricha l'ara*.
Apparently, you know, sometimes you would cut down grain and you'd leave
it spread out on the ground so that it would like dry
out. So you could say if I'm selling it to you, then
maybe now if I say כל מה שבתוכה *kol ma shebetocha*, it
goes with it. But without saying כל מה שבתוכה *kol ma shebetocha*,
even though that grain is using and needs the ground, I sold
you the ground, I didn't sell you the grain once it's been
cut. ולא את חצצת הקנים שהיא בית רובע *V'lo et hitzas hakanim
shehi beis rova*, not this patch of growing reeds that's the size
of a בית רובע *beis rova*. ואף על פי דקטיני *V'af al
pi dikatini*. Again, like the flip of the other case. The other
case is if it's smaller than that size, even though they're thick,
you do sell it. If it's this size or larger, even though
they're very thin, you don't sell it. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan*, לא
חצצת הקנים בלבד *lo hitzas hakanim bilvad*. It's not just a section
of reeds. And again we go to the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*'s idea,
any plot within that land that would be considered a different field,
not the same field, wouldn't go with the field. And that's even
if you say כל מה שבתוכה *kol ma shebetocha*. So he says
this isn't limited to a section of reeds, אלא אפילו ערוגה קטנה
שבבשמים *ela afilu aruga ktana shebe'bsamim*, even if it's a little patch
where you're growing spices. Okay, but now what makes it a separate
identity? ויש לה שם בפני עצמה *V'yesh lah shem bifnei atzmah*. It
has its own separate name. Like you don't just say, like you
know you say "Oh yeah, you know I've got some wild roses
growing here, oh yeah we have some cinnamon that grows over here,"
that's part of the field. But if you say "This is our
cinnamon patch," then that's its separate identity. Alright. ויש לה שם בפני
עצמה אינה נמכרת עמה *V'yesh lah shem bifnei atzmah einah nimkeres imah*.
אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa*, והוא דקרי לה ורדא דפלניא *vehu
dekari leh varda d'planya*. So it gives an example. It says it's
like you called it... now ורדא *varda* is roses, that's why my
sister's name is ורדה *Varda*, so I meant to tell her that
today's דף *daf* mentions her name. Anyway,
so it says roses, but the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says that it
basically means like the spice garden, so and so's spice garden. But
I don't know, so and so's roses, "Oh yeah, that's Shimon's rose
garden." So if it's got that separate identity, it's not "Oh yeah,
those are the roses that grow in Shimon's land," but that's "Shimon's
rose garden." So if I'm selling you my field, you don't get
the rose garden, I just said the field. Yes? But I imagine
a field that is full of like "There's the cinnamon patch and
there's the carrot row and there's the..." so isn't it all just
like what are you selling? Right, so I guess that if it's
like a field that is all of these different spices then I'm
selling the field then it is, then they are. I was sort
of thinking about it that I basically grow wheat here and in
this little section I have a little hobby and I grow some
roses and I got a rose patch. That's the way I was
imagining it. The majority of the field... Yeah, you're right. I mean
if the whole field is a field of flowers or a field
of spices and they're different sections, then yes, I assume that it's
all the spices field. ערוגה *Aruga*, it's
a little... Right, exactly. It's but it's like of a different... of
a different סוג *sug* than the other stuff that's growing in the
field. Yes. Just so you know, ורדא *varda* is an Iranian word
for rose. There you go.
So I don't know why the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* interprets it otherwise,
but I will now tell my sister that the word
is... I know it's a lily, but I know, but it says
בין החוחים, so it's got thorns. Lilies don't have thorns. שושנה shoshana
is quite possibly a rose. What you mean it's like thorn bushes?
No, no, I always understood it metaphorically that there's this one beautiful
flower growing in the middle of the thorns. Oh,
I see. I see. I see. Okay, fine. It's very romantic. It
can't
be—she can't be thorny. Okay, that's true. That's true. Okay, fine. All
right, moving on. ולו השומירה עשויה בטיט. v'lo hashomera asuya b'tit. You
also don't sell, according to our version of it, the hut that
is plastered over. That's like its own house, its own identity. דאף
על גב דמחברה בארעא, d'af al gav d'mechabera b'ara, according to this
version that the more permanent it is, so no. So now, it's
one thing that it's—and it's connected to the ground, and you might
think that connected to the ground makes it part of the ground.
No, this retains its own identity. Okay. ולא חרוב המורכב ולא סדן
השקמה, v'lo charuv hamurkav v'lo sadan hashikma, for that's if that's our
גרסא, Girsah אף על גב דקטיני, af al gav d'katini, once they
have been grafted and you know, you know, cut or whatever and
they've reached that next stage of maturity, even if they are not
big trees, they have an independent identity. That's particularly, I think, a
חידוש chiddush once we're saying that even if you say כל המחובר
בתוכה. kol hamuchbar b'tocha. Okay. בעי רב אליעזר. ba'ei Rav Eliezer. Rabbi
Eliezer asks, מלבנות של פתחים מהו? malbenot shel petachim mahu? What about
doorframes? Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says we're asking סתם, stam, I sell
you my house, do you get the doorframe with it? Okay, now
for us it seems like absurd because they're built into the wall.
But apparently there what they would sometimes do is they might, after
you build the house, go ahead and like nail in a doorframe.
Like a doorframe would be a separate thing that they would attach
on afterwards. That's exactly the way they build things now. Doorframes are
separate.
Well, this doorframe is like built in. Usually separate piece.
Oh, but oh, true, but once it's built—but once it's built in,
okay, right, that's true. That's true. Okay, that's true. That's true. You're
right. You're right. What? How do you take out? Right, so that's,
I think, what I was trying to explain. Like here, there's no
way you could remove it, whereas there, it could have—it was like
could be like nailed in and you could seriously remove it. You
could remove this. It's not structural. Aha.
If I take out—away that doorframe, it'll take me—it's a טרחא, tircha,
right, but I took it
away, the wall stays. Interesting. Okay. All right, interesting. Okay, so let's
go on. Now, by the way, תוספות Tosafot doesn't like the idea
that we are all of a sudden now talking about what happens
if you sell a house. So תוספות Tosafot says we're still talking
about the hut. Like you sold the hut when you sell the
hut with the field, whenever that case is, like מחובר לטיט muchbar
l'tit and whatever, anyway, or you say you're selling the hut, like
does the doorframe go with it? It's the same question essentially, but
he makes it more directly about what we're talking about. Okay. So
מהו. mahu. So היכא דמחבר בטינא, heicha d'mechabar b'tina, if it's connected
with like plaster, with like you know, tar, לא תיבעי לך, lo
tiba'ei lach, then like or cement, דהא מחובר, d'ha mechubar, then that
it's really it's physically one unit, of course it's sold with it.
כי תיבעי לך דנקיטי בסיכי, ki tiba'ei lach d'nekitei b'siki,
that it's banged in with nails. Okay. מאי, mai, so what's the
story? Do I get to remove the doorframe? I just take out
the nails. תיקו. teiku. We don't know the answer to that. That's
pretty amazing. You would think if you're selling a house and they're
banged in doorframes, it goes with it. Yes. I mean, the way
I read the question, yes, as well, is like that's what I
thought he was doing. Like they're in the middle of this conversation,
they're talking about, like, do you get the tree that's in the
field, and he's like, do you get the doorframe that's in the
house? Right. Or rhetorical. Oh, you mean it's like ironic. Like, of
course you get it.
That's an interesting way of reading the דף, right. Okay, so the
רשב"ם Rashbam says now what would be the logic? I mean, the
way the רשב"ם Rashbam tries to make sense of it, he says
מי אמרינן אינן צריכים לפתח כל כך. mi amrinan einan tzrichim lapetach
kol kach. Yeah, you can have a door without a doorframe. You
don't really need it. It's a nice add-on. Okay. At some places,
the רשב"ם Rashbam here says yeah, it's mostly aesthetic. It's not really
functional. Like, I don't know, it depends on your doorframe, I guess.
I can't just depict—I understand—I do not understand how this is going
to work without—how this could not be sold with the door. I
don't understand how the wall would stand up. Oh, yeah, I don't
know. Okay. בעי רב זירא. ba'ei Rav Zeira. All right. מלבנות של
חלונות מהו? malbenot shel chalonot mahu? How about a window frame? What's
the story there? Like, okay, a doorframe is more functional, but maybe
a window frame—maybe that is sold with it. But a window frame,
maybe that's more purely aesthetic. Okay. מהו. mahu.
מי אמרינן לנוי בעלמא עבידי, mi amrinan lenoy be'alma avidi, it's just
for, you know, aesthetics? או דילמא כיון דמחברי מחברי, o dilma keivan
d'mechabrei mechabrei,
once it's connected, attached, it's attached. תיקו. teiku. Okay. בעי רב ירמיה.
ba'ei Rav Yirmiya. מלבנות של כרעי המיטה
מהו? malbenot shel karei hamita mahu? How about some type of a
frame for a bed? Now, the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains this,
I'm wondering what your Steinsaltz and others say. He makes it sound
like it's basically just some type of a—of a—like a... Like you
know when you buy get tables or whatever and you don't want
or for your chairs and you don't want it to scratch the
floor, you buy these little pads underneath it? So he basically describes
something like that although not to protect the floor, he says in
order so that the legs of the bed don't rot. Yeah, there's
a picture they're like boxes. Oh they're boxes that you put into
you put the legs into? Okay fine. So what's the story with
those? כל היכא דמטלטל בהדיה לא תיבעי לך. kol heicha demitaltel bahadei
lo tiba'ei lach. If it moves when you move the bed,
then okay that's part of the bed and that clearly is functional.
כי תיבעי לך היכא דלא מטלטל ki tiba'ei lach heicha delo mitaltel
if it doesn't move when you move the bed, but that's something
maybe like the flip where it's clearly recognized as functional but it's
not physically attached. So מהו מאי mahu mai what would you say?
If you sold the bed did you sell these? תיקו. teku. It's
according to the רשב"ם Rashbam if I understand correctly שלא ירקבו בקרקע.
shelo yirkavu bakarka. Right. So it's a the floor is soil.
Right. Right. Yeah to protect the of from termites, that's interesting. ולא
חרוב המורכב ולא סדן השקמה velo charuv hamurkav velo sadan hashikmah and
you do not sell these trees once they get to this age
of maturity where they're being cut and grafted and so on. Okay
so now the
גמרא says מנא הני מילי manan hanei milei where's this from? That
there's times when you basically assume that you generally sell the trees
within a field but there's some trees that are not sold within
a field. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב דאמר קרא amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav de'amar kra oh look a פסוק! pasuk! ויקם שדה עפרון
vayakam sdei Efron anytime you get a פסוק pasuk you gotta appreciate.
Okay right? Same פסוק pasuk as someone brought up before.
We brought up this פסוק pasuk earlier? Yeah. Just where? When? When
did we bring? Like 10 דפים. dappim. Really? ויקם שדה עפרון אשר
במכפלה אשר לפני ממרא השדה והמערה אשר בו וכל העץ אשר בשדה
אשר בכל גבולו סביב. vayakam sdei Efron asher bamachpelah asher lifnei mamre
hasadeh vehamarah asher bo vechol ha'etz asher basadeh asher bechol gvulov saviv.
So it's וכל העץ אשר בשדה אשר בכל גבולו סביב. vechol ha'etz
asher basadeh asher bechol gvulov saviv. So as a standard when you
buy a שדה sadeh you get כל עץ kol etz you get
all the trees. Okay but now how do you know there are
trees you don't get? Because it ends by saying אשר בכל גבולו
סביב asher bechol gvulov saviv that's in the entire boundary. מי שצריך
לגבול סביב mi shetzarich ligvul saviv something that basically needs the boundaries
around it. יצאו אלו שאין צריכין לגבול סביב yatzu elu she'ein tzerichin
ligvul saviv this doesn't need the boundaries around it. What does that
mean? So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains it let me just
double check the רמב"ן Ramban the רשב"ם Rashbam oh right the רשב"ם
Rashbam says that if you've got a normal field
here okay this is my field and this is your field and
we've got some like normal trees growing we've got like a patch
of trees growing here right we might not we need a boundary
to tell me where it is because it's not exactly clear we
could wind up arguing that tree's in my field it's over my
line that's over my line. So you need a boundary. But if
you've got one of these trees I mean okay this is like
just reading your own assumptions into the פסוק pasuk right? But if
you've got one of these trees like a big tree because it's
so important there's never going to be a confusion whose field it
was in. We've always known whose field it was in. Right a
little small little tree like we could forget was that in your
side of the line or my side of the line? But something
as significant as this we'll never everybody will always remember whose field
that was in. That's at least the way we're reading it. So
trees that are significant that are clearly identifiable and so on are
ones that we say don't are not just naturally go with the
field. All right tell me that's not so much פשט pshat in
the פסוק pasuk you're not going to get an argument. Moving on.
השדה בפני עצמו. hasadeh bifnei atzmo. Right. Right. אמר רב משרשיא מכאן
למצרים מן התורה amar Rav Mesharsheya mikan lemeitzarin min hatorah
from here you see the idea of boundaries in the תורה. Torah.
What does that mean? So the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains what
it means is that if you buy the field you also buy
the boundary line of the field. I never really explained it because
the boundary line has to be on one person's side or the
other person's side but I guess it means if there are like
trees that make up the boundary line you know they go with
the field. But like of course if they're part of the field
I mean if they belong to שמעון Shimon and שמעון Shimon sold
you his field he sells you the trees that are part of
the boundary line if they belong to ראובן Reuven he doesn't. If
they're neither ראובן's Reuven nor שמעון's Shimon or they're half and half
he doesn't sell like I don't exactly get the חידוש. chidush. I
mean you can read the רשב"ם Rashbam you can tell me what
you think he means the first wide line here מכאן למצרים מן
התורה שהקונה את השדה קנה את המצרים עצמן וכל האילנות הנטועין במצר
המצרים בכלל שדה. mikan lemeitzarin min hatorah shehakoneh et hasadeh kanah et
hameitzarin atzman vechol ha'ilanot hanetuin bameitzar hameitzarin bichlal sadeh.
The boundary lines are part of the field like I don't know
to me that would be obvious. If the guy who's selling you
the field owns the boundary line to me that would be clear.
Anyway דהכי משמע סביב dehachi mashma saviv right וכל עץ אשר בשדה
אשר בכל גבולו סביב vechol ha'etz asher basadeh asher bechol gvulov saviv
around. כל האילנות הנטועין בארעא kol ha'ilanot hanetuin be'ar'a
all the trees even the ones that make up the boundary line.
המצר שהוא סביב השדה קנה אברהם. hameitzar shehu saviv hasadeh kanah Avraham.
So you get all the trees around it even the trees that
are part of the boundary line. So I guess somebody shouldn't claim
I sold you the field but this whole patch of trees that
serves as a boundary line that's a separate thing. אהני דקלא. ahani
dikla. Yeah I know I understand. can, I'm just saying like I
guess to me it would be obvious since the function of the
trees is to serve as a boundary line and you're selling the
field. Okay, maybe there's some חידוש, chiddush, maybe you could have thought
the guy could have claimed, "I sold you the field, but I
kept the boundary trees for myself." It's like you rent an apartment,
right? Right. Everything that's in the apartment you're responsible for, right, you're
in charge, but anything that's inside the walls, right, is now the
building, it's like how much are you... Okay. All right. So that's
the חידוש chiddush that when you sell the field it also comes
with the trees that are serving as the boundary. אמר רב יהודה.
Amar Rav Yehuda. האי מאן דמזבין ארעא לחבריה. Hai man de'mazbin ara
le'chavrei. Now we're going to actually get to what some documents actually
look like. Somebody who sells some land to his friend, צריך למיכתב
ליה, tzarich lemichtav lei, קני לך דקלי וטלין והוצין וציצין. kni lach
diklin ve'talin ve'hutzin ve'tzitzin. So there's an exact question of exactly what
these words mean. According to the Soncino, a דקלא dekla we know
is a palm tree. The Soncino says דקלא dekla is like a
mature palm tree, טלין talin is like other trees that are not
palm trees, הוצין hutzin is an immature palm tree, and ציצין tzitzin
is immature other trees. That's the way the Soncino has it. The
רשב"ם Rashbam has a version that these are all different types of
palm trees. I don't know. Anyway, if you're trying to sell all
the trees, the standard thing to write is this type of a
phrase which basically says I'm selling you everything: the palm trees, the
other trees, the young ones, the old ones. Okay, that's what you
write. And then he says ואף על גב דלא כתב ליה הכי
קני, ve'af al gav de'la katav lei hachi kani, you really don't
have to write that. We just got through saying in our משנה
that when you sell the field, all the trees go with it,
right? That's automatic other than these sycamore trees or whatever. אפילו הכי
שופרא דשטרא הוא. Afilu hachi shufra d'sh'tara hu. That's a nice phrase,
שופרא דשטרא, shufra d'sh'tara, an embellishment of the שטר. shtar. It's like,
you know, it's not exactly the boilerplate, but שופרא דשטרא shufra d'sh'tara
is like it makes the שטר shtar nicer. It makes more explicit
things that otherwise would not have been explicit. And the benefit is,
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam says it, at least the benefit is
just so there shouldn't be any question. Even though we do know
that's the standard language, or maybe it comes to a בית דין
beis din that isn't so learned, so you know, to make things
a little more explicit never hurt. All right. Of course, that's not
always true. I don't know, we have a lawyer here, but you
know, sometimes it's like כל המוסיף גורע, kol hamosif goreia, right? If
you make things more explicit then maybe you're actually coming to say
something different than what the default understanding would have been. And we're
actually going to get to a possibility like that coming up. Okay.
So anyway, but that's the claim. This is like a standard thing
to write which isn't technically necessary, but it makes the שטר shtar
nicer. Okay. אמר ליה ארעא ודקלי. Amar lei ara ve'diklei. So he
says to him, "I am selling you land and palm trees." Okay.
So presumably, since the palm trees go with the land, the "and
palm trees" is read as in addition to the sale of this
land, I'm also selling you palm trees. And then you have to
figure out like if this guy's got other palm trees, then those
are also sold. So I own here, here's some land I own
here, right in New York, this plot of land, and then somewhere
where do palm trees grow, in Florida, somewhere down here in Florida
I've got some palm trees. I can't grow palm trees... Okay, anyway.
So I say I'm selling you land and palm trees. So do
we read this the land and the palm trees in it? No,
because land includes palm trees in it. I didn't say land with
palm trees, I said land and palm trees. So I sold you
this plot of land plus I sold you some palm trees. How
many palm trees? Okay. חזינן, Chazinan, we see. אי אית ליה דקלי,
Ei is lei diklei, if he has palm trees somewhere else, יהיב
ליה תרי דקלי, yehiv lei t'rei diklei, give him two palm trees.
That's the minimum of palm trees. You get to pick which two.
Okay. ואי לית ליה, Ve'ei leis lei, and if I don't own
any other palm trees, so what? I said I sold you that
and palm trees. How am I going to keep up my end
of the bargain? ואי לית ליה זבין ליה תרי דקלי, Ve'ei leis
lei zavin lei t'rei diklei, go buy him two palm trees so
that then you can keep it up. Now, of course you don't
have to buy if I said I'm selling you something I don't
own, I could just give you your money back. But the רשב"ם
Rashbam says, "Yeah, but you know, you want to sort of keep
your integrity, keep your sense of trust." So therefore, you could give
the money back, but you'd be better off buying the palm trees
and delivering them to the guy. "Oh, I went there. Where are
the palm trees?" "They're being delivered today." Yeah, except I think they
have to be attached to the ground. ואי משעבדי, Ve'ei meshubadi, if
you do have palm trees but
they're encumbered, somebody has a lien on them, פריק ליה, parik lei,
so buy off, pay off your debt and so that the guy
can get the palm trees. It's so funny like why do you
have to say that? Anyway. Okay, פריק ליה. parik lei. Now, that's
the end of that. Now, that's the way the רשב"ם explains it.
The רשב"ם says that the word means palm trees outside of the
land. But תוספות Tosafot read it in a way that really challenges
the line right before in the גמרא. Because תוספות Tosafot actually read
it that I have palm trees in here. Okay. And even if
I had said nothing, I'd just say, "I'm selling you the land,"
you would have got all the palm trees. If I say, "I'm
selling you land and
palm
trees..." Like better to say less, you know, if it's clearly included,
because you'll say more and maybe the way you phrase it will
actually mean no, not all the palm trees, just some of the
palm trees. So if you take a look תוספות Tosafot says ארעא
ודיקלי אי אית בה דיקלי, Ara Vedikli ee it bah dikli, so
so he says he so תוספות Tosafot has the גרסא Girsah not
our גרסא Girsah is אי אית לה דיקלי ee it lah dikli
if you own palm trees. תוספות Tosafot גרסא is אי אית בה
דיקלי ee it bah dikli if there are palm trees in the
plot of land. דאף על גב דאם לא אמר דיקלי בסתמא היו
כולן מכורין De'af al gav de'im lo amar dikli bistama hayu kulan
mekhurin when you just say I'm selling you the land it goes
with all the trees, מיהו השתא גרע. Mihu hashta gara.
Here you made it worse because you said and the palm trees.
So one wonders how's that different between what he said before דיקלין
וטליין והוצין וציצין. diklin vetalayin vehutzin vetzitzin.
You know, I'm not exactly clear, maybe it was the use of
the ו. vav. Anyway, here somehow because you said more you wound
up it came out meaning less. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads
it. Let's go back to the גמרא. Our first wide line ארעא
בדיקלי ara bedikli I am selling you the land with its palm
trees. Okay, so that clearly you're referring to palm trees in the
land but once again you didn't have to say that. The palm
trees would have been part of the package so חזינן hazinan we
see אי אית בה דיקלי יהיב ליה. ee it bah dikli yahev
leh. Alright, if there are palm trees that goes with. You said
with its palm trees, that means with all its palm trees. So
maybe when we said before שופרא דשטרא shufra de'shtara was when you
used the letter ב. be So if you said I'm selling it
to you what was the phrase before ב the land בדיקלין וטליין
והוצין וציצין bediklin vetalayin vehutzin vetzitzin it means with all of them.
But if you use the letter ו vav I'm selling it to
you and this, oh and that means that you're seeing the trees
as separate from the land so you're not selling all the trees.
That's at least the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. But let's say
he doesn't say any reference to the דיקלי. dikli. Then they go
with it. Why? It could have been a שדה בפני עצמה. sadeh
bifnei atzmah. No that's no I mean if they are a שדה
בפני עצמה sadeh bifnei atzmah but the משנה assumes basically that trees
go with the land. But what about the שקמא? shikmah? The שקמא
shikmah is separate. The שקמא shikmah and the חרוב charuv yeah but
we're talking about palm trees. We're talking about palm trees because those
are classic trees that are sold with the land. It's only the
שקמא shikmah and the חרוב. charuv. Those are the two exceptions. I'm
sorry, I didn't get no it's not generalizable. It is only the
sycamore and the carob. He'd like to be individualized. וכל עץ אשר
בשדה vechol etz asher basadeh that's what we learned. Normal עץ etz
is sold with the field. Okay alright so is a דקא deka
what? A palm tree? It's some kind of tree. No.
It's very big, I know. Right,
so is it?
I don't know, for some reason it I know I would have
thought that it might be more like a carob I would have
thought it's also this huge tree it would have been more like
a carob and a sycamore but it's treated as this is an
example of a standard tree that is sold with the field. Let's
just we finish reading this front I'll get to you in a
second Jemmy. He says okay ארעא בדיקלי חזינן אי
אית בה
דיקלי יהיב ליה. ara bedikli hazinan ee it bah dikli yahev leh.
If there are you give because and then the words didn't add
anything you would have gotten it anyway but okay. ואי לאו ve'ee
lav but here's the חידוש chiddush מקח טעות הוא. mekach ta'ut hu.
If it turns out that there were no palm trees growing in
that land, you sold said you sold me a field with palm
trees. So if there's no palm trees, you saw I you know
you you sold me you lied. This was not what I bought.
So the רשב"ם says it's not a problem that I overpaid. The
principle is אין אונאה בקרקעות. ein ona'ah bekarka'ot. So if I paid
something and then after you sold it to me I got it
assessed and I found out you charged me ten times its worth,
it's not a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. But if you say I'm
selling you a wheat field and it turns out to be an
apple orchard, it's a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. So if you say
you're telling me a field with palm trees and it's a field
that doesn't have palm trees it's a מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. So
the with even without saying anything I would have got the palm
trees but by adding the with you've basically said that it has
to have those or that's not the field that I'm selling. Jana
you had a question. I was just gonna ask about the דיקלי
dikli like that's something that you have a lot of in a
field and they're like intentionally there because you're purposely trying to grow
something. Uh-huh, so
you mean it might be a sycamore it's a one-off, right? Like
it doesn't work as territory. Uh-huh, so you mean it might just
that's part of what makes it independent that you don't have like
a patch of them and you don't right could be. It's like
one big tree. Right right right generally see a sycamore. Right right
right that could be right it is each one is sort of
like independent and it's not yeah. So if you overpay if it's
a matter of שטות shtut so the מקח mekach is not called
מקח טעות. mekach ta'ut. Correct, not by קרקע. karka. Now there is
a position
of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that says that if it's double, if
if it's overcharged by a hundred percent it is מקח טעות. mekach
ta'ut. But the point here of מקח טעות mekach ta'ut is not
that it was you paid too much. Maybe you even got a
bargain. The point was you didn't get what you were told you
were going to get. You were told... The point was you didn't
get what you were told you were going to get. You were
told you were going to get a field with palm trees. No,
but I forgot that overcharging applies for קרקע, karka, in which case
the third case would work out, right? Because he says it's a
place, a place for palms? No, no, that's the third case. Okay,
now, next case. אתרא דדקלי, Atra d'diklei, let's say I say I
am selling you land that is a place for palm trees, a
land that's good for palm trees, you know, where palm trees can
grow. לית
דקלי, Leit diklei,
then you don't get any palm trees even if they're... I'm just
saying that it's fit for growing palm trees, doesn't mean that I'm
promising you that there are palm trees. Now, of course, the question
is, does that mean לית דקלי leit diklei even if there are
palm trees there, I get to remove them even though if I
had said nothing you would have gotten the palm trees? So the
רשב"ם says let me remind myself what the רשב"ם says about this.
מקום הראוי לדקלי לית דקלי כי אם אין דקלי אין זה מקח
טעות. Makom haraui lediklei leit diklei ki im ein diklei ein zeh
mekach taut. So the רשב"ם doesn't say that. No, I don't get
to remove palm trees that are there. I told you it was
a land that was good for growing palm trees, you get the
palm trees that are there. If I had said nothing, you get
the palm trees. This is the way he reads it. It's not
necessarily clear in the גמרא. But what it means is you can't
complain. In the previous case, if there were no palm trees, you
get your money back if it's מקח טעות. mekach taut. Here, I
didn't promise you palm trees, I promised you a place for palm
trees. And therefore, if there are no palm trees, then you cannot,
you have no טענה taina against me. Okay?
דחזי לדקלי קאמר ליה, Dechazi lediklei ka'amar lei, because he said it
was fit for דקלי, diklei, I didn't say there were דקלי. diklei.
אמר ליה לבר מדיקלא, Amar lei l'bar midikla, I say פלניא, planya,
so I say I am selling you this field except for that
palm tree over there. All right, so what's the question? You made
it very clear. So here's the issue. חזינן, Chazinan, we look. אי
דקלא טבא הוא, Ei dikla tava hu, if that was a, the
way the רשב"ם explains, was not a necessarily like a particularly good
tree, but like a good tree, it was a normal good producing
palm tree, so שיורי שיירי, shiurei sheyarei, so then that was a
tree you left for yourself. We just treat your words literally. You
wanted to keep one palm tree. You know, you loved growing your
dates and your palm trees, so even though you had to sell
it, you wanted to keep one for yourself. גזונטהייט. Gezuntheit. Okay. But
אי דקלא בישא הוא, ei dikla bisha hu, but let's say this
is a non-producing, this is the way the רשב"ם reads it, palm
tree. So what are you doing by keeping it? Like, what's the
point? Okay? Like, you're not going to get any, you know, any
dates out of it. So he says כל שכן הני, kol sheken
hanei, so then what we say he means is, because this is
really interesting, he means even this palm tree I keep for myself,
even the bad one, and certainly I keep the good ones and
the producing ones. So that's like a big חידוש. chiddush. I say
I am leaving for myself this one bad palm tree, and because
that's such a bizarre thing to be doing, we're going to interpret
it as I'm leaving myself all the palm trees up to and
including this bad one. All right, so that's a very, I don't
know, to me that's a huge חידוש. chiddush.
All right. So now the גמרא says like this.
אמר ליה לבר מאילני, Amar lei l'bar me'ilani, okay, now we're going
to see the difference of trees and palm trees. I'm selling you
this field except for the trees in it. So אי אית ליה
אילני, ei it lei ilani, so לבר מאילני, l'bar me'ilani, if you
have trees, then okay, you sold the field minus the trees. אי
אית ליה דקלי, Ei it lei diklei, now let's say you have
trees, you don't have trees, other trees, but you have palm trees.
So we're going to see that palm trees are like one degree
less part of the field. They're not at the status of the
carob and the sycamore, but they're not like just סתם stam any
normal tree. So if you say minus the trees, it's all the
other trees that you're keeping to yourself. Okay? But
if you don't have any other trees, then we'll say that that
word refers to the palm trees. אי אית ליה דקלי Ei it
lei diklei לבר מדקלי, l'bar midiklei, then we'll interpret it to mean
you're keeping the palm trees for yourself. אי אית ליה גופני, Ei
it lei gufnei, if however there's no normal trees and there's no
palm trees, so how do we interpret your word except for the
trees? Well, if you have
vines, grapevines, לבר מגופני, l'bar migufnei, we'll interpret it that way. Okay?
So we'll give that word whatever, you know, it has to have
some meaning, we'll give it its most basic meaning, but if that
meaning doesn't fit, then we'll go down the line to see what
other meaning most likely fits that word. All right, so but normally
it wouldn't refer to palm trees or grapevines, but if you have
no other choice, you'll say that's what it refers to. Okay. לבר
מגופני. L'bar migufnei. Now of course you understand that this is why
somebody wants to hire a lawyer, because here I am buying David's
field from him and I, or no, I am selling my field
to David and I'm going to write in this "except for the
trees" and David's chuckling to himself, he says "haha, great, there are
no trees in that field." And then I say, "oh, there are
no trees in that field, so except for the trees," and he's
like "I get to keep all the vines for myself, right?" So
you really gotta know what you're doing here. Okay. Okay, now אילני
וגופני, ilani vegufnei, לבר מאילני, l'bar me'ilani, I'm sorry, where were we?
אי
אית ליה גופני לבר מגופני Ei it lei gufnei l'bar migufnei אילני
וגופני. ilani vegufnei. לבר מאילני *lebar mi-ilani* hold on now I gotta
remember how to read this hold on a
second now I got lost
you say אילני וגופני *ilani vegufnei* one minute גופני ודקלי *gufnei
vediklei* לבר מאילני *lebar mi-ilni* oh okay I got it one minute
let me see if that's it he says גופני *gufnei* לבר מגופני
*lebar migufni* אילני וגופני *ilani vegufni* right oh so I said right
I got it I said I said except for the trees now
I have both trees and grapevines so what if I have both
trees and grapevines so לבר מאילני *lebar mi-ilani* it only means except
for the trees it doesn't include the grapevines what if I say
אילני ודקלי *ilani vediklei* let's say I have trees and palm trees
and I said except for the trees לבר מאילני *lebar mi-ilani* so
it just excludes the trees it doesn't exclude the palm trees I
don't get to keep the palm trees okay that's sort of all
implicit from what we said before now let's say I have גופני
ודקלי *gufnei vediklei* I don't have any normal trees but I have
grapevines and palm trees and I said except for the trees which
one of those
two no no I said we're all the case no it's all
the same case that I said except for the trees but the
scenario is that all I own are grapevines and palm trees which
of the two does it apply to okay if I have trees
plus any other plus you know if A is trees
now use the Hebrew words okay A is trees B is דקלים
*dekalim*
and C is גפנים *gefanim* okay and I say לבר מ *lebar
mi* trees okay so if I have trees plus anything else it
just means trees okay if I don't have trees and I have
one of these alone I have just B or just C then
it means just B or just C okay let's say I don't
have trees and I have B and C how do I explain
the scope which of these two does it apply to that's our
question which one do you keep which one do I keep until
now we said that as long as I have trees it only
means the trees even if I had all three of these it
only meant the trees if I didn't have trees and I had
one of these it meant one of them but if I don't
have trees and I have both of these which of those two
does it mean and how do you based on what we've said
you keep the גפנים *gefanim* because דקלי *diklei* goes with the list
so far we've been
structuring it like דקל *dekel* is a closer meaning than גפן *gefen*
but we haven't been explicit about it so let's take a look
so גופני ודקלי *gufnei vediklei* if I had both palm trees and
grapevines לבר מגופני *lebar migufnei* then I get to actually keep the
גפנים *gefanim* now why is that the buildup until now had made
it think like it would be the דקלים *dekalim* so one of
the explanations the רשב"ם *Rashbam* gives is like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
*hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya* that the גפנים *gefanim* are we can presume
are of more value than the דקלים *dekalim* and since like you
know I'm in possession of it I get to say that's what
it meant because it could equally mean both that's one explanation that
he says what well because before there was a clear meaning like
before it was this plus something of one of these and it
was clear that you only had you know what the meaning was
but here there's really indeterminate which one of those two you might
mean so we so that's one explanation it's המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
*hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya* the other explanation let me just see what
he says is
לבר מגופני *lebar migufnei* no the other explanation he just says is
that the word אילן *ilan* more applies to a גפן *gefen* than
to a דקל *dekel* which is a little hard to believe so
if you don't have אילני *ilani* and you don't have אילנות *ilanos*
he says you say you could use yeah before he said if
you don't have אילני *ilani* but you have one of these the
word can apply to either now we're asking which one does it
apply to more before we said you didn't have אילני *ilani* you
didn't have trees but you had these and it would have applied
to B you only had one of them now we're saying that
you don't have trees and you have both which one does it
apply to more it's funny to me is right why do they
need to clarify which of those two is closer to the term
אילני *ilani* like a formalistic question whereas the operative principle in דין
*din* I'm buying your field and there are palm trees on it
palm trees go with the field yeah
but you also made explicit an exception it raises I think also
interesting question who's the מוחזק *muchzak* who's whatever but the principles it's
not an so interesting of a גמרא *Gemara* because you could understand
that there's interesting principles at play here right who's the מוחזק *muchzak*
how do you deal with ספק *safek* or whatever but it doesn't
tell us that all it just tells us here's what the word
means yeah I mean
isn't that like a